I want to ask you all to consider for a second
أود أن أسأل الجميع الأخذ بعين الإعتبار و للحظة
the very simple fact
الحقيقة الجد بسيطة
that, by far,
حيث أنه و بنسبة جد عالية،
most of what we know about the universe
معظم ما نعلمه عن الكون
comes to us from light.
يأتينا من الضوء.
We can stand on the Earth and look up at the night sky
يمكننا الوقوف فوق الأرض و تأمل السماء المظلم
and see stars with our bare eyes.
و رؤية النجوم بأعيننا العارية.
The Sun burns our peripheral vision.
تحرق الشمس رؤيتنا الجانبية،
We see light reflected off the Moon.
نرى إنعكاس الضوء فوق سطح القمر،
And in the time since Galileo pointed that rudimentary telescope
و منذ أن وجه غاليليو منظاره البدائي
at the celestial bodies,
نحو الأجسام السماوية،
the known universe has come to us through light,
قدم إلينا الكون المنظور عن طريق الضوء،
across vast eras in cosmic history.
عبر عصور فسيحة من التاريخ الكوني.
And with all of our modern telescopes,
و بواسطة كل منظاراتنا الحديثة،
we've been able to collect
تمكنا من جمع
this stunning silent movie of the universe --
هذا الشريط الكوني الصامت و المذهل --
these series of snapshots
هذه اللقطات المتسلسلة
that go all the way back to the Big Bang.
التي تصف طريق العودة إلى الإنفجار العظيم.
And yet, the universe is not a silent movie
رغم ذالك، فإن الكون ليس بشريط صامت،
because the universe isn't silent.
لأن الكون ليس صامتا.
I'd like to convince you
أود أن أقنعكم
that the universe has a soundtrack
أن الكون له صوت،
and that soundtrack is played on space itself,
و أن هذا الصوت يغنى على الفضاء نفسه.
because space can wobble like a drum.
لأن الفضاء يتذبذب كالطبل.
It can ring out a kind of recording
يمكنه سماع نوعا من التسجيل
throughout the universe
عبر الكون
of some of the most dramatic events as they unfold.
لأحد أقوى الأحداث خلال ظهورها.
Now we'd like to be able to add
نريد الآن التمكن من إضافة
to a kind of glorious visual composition
لهذه التركيبة البصرية المجيدة
that we have of the universe --
التي نملك عن الكون
a sonic composition.
تركيبة صوتية.
And while we've never heard the sounds from space,
و حيث لم نسمع أبدا الأصوات القادمة من الفضاء،
we really should, in the next few years,
يجب علينا، خلال الأعوام القادمة،
start to turn up the volume on what's going on out there.
البدء بالإنصات لما يحدث هناك.
So in this ambition
و في طموح
to capture songs from the universe,
لإستقطاب أناشيد الكون،
we turn our focus
نوجه تركيزنا
to black holes and the promise they have,
نحو الثقب السوداء و ما تعدنا به،
because black holes can bang on space-time
لأن الثقب السوداء تضرب الزمكان
like mallets on a drum
كضرب العصا على الطبل
and have a very characteristic song,
و إن لهم أغنية جد مميزة،
which I'd like to play for you -- some of our predictions
و أود أن أسمعكم بعضا من توقعاتنا
for what that song will be like.
لما قد تبدوا عليه هذه الأغنية.
Now black holes are dark against a dark sky.
إن الثقب السوداء أجسام مظلمة في سماء مظلم.
We can't see them directly.
لا يمكن أن نشاهدها مباشرة.
They're not brought to us with light, at least not directly.
لا تحمل إلينا عن طريق الضوء، ليس بصفة مباشرة على الأقل.
We can see them indirectly,
يمكن لنا رؤيتهم بصفة غير مباشرة،
because black holes wreak havoc on their environment.
لأن الثقب السوداء تعيث خرابا في محيطها.
They destroy stars around them.
إنها تدمر النجوم المحيطة بها.
They churn up debris in their surroundings.
إنها تقذف حطاما في محيطها.
But they won't come to us directly through light.
لكنها لن تأتي إلينا عبر الضوء.
We might one day see a shadow
يمكن أن نرى يوما ما ظلا
a black hole can cast on a very bright background,
ألقاه ثقب أسود على خالفية لامعة،
but we haven't yet.
لكن لم نرى ذلك بعد.
And yet black holes may be heard
و رغم ذلك يمكن سماع الثقب السوداء
even if they're not seen,
حتى إذا لم يتم مشاهدتها،
and that's because they bang on space-time like a drum.
و ذلك لأنها تضرب على الزمكان كالطبل.
Now we owe the idea that space can ring like a drum
ندين بفكرة أن الفضاء يرتد مثل الطبل
to Albert Einstein -- to whom we owe so much.
إلى ألبيرت أينشتاين، إنا ندين له الكثير.
Einstein realized that if space were empty,
أدرك أنشتاين أنه إذا كان الفضاء فارغا،
if the universe were empty,
إذا كان الكون فارغا،
it would be like this picture,
فسيكون كهذه الصورة،
except for maybe without the helpful grid drawn on it.
بإستثناء الشبكة الإيضاحية المرسومة عليها.
But if we were freely falling through the space,
لكن إذا سقطنا بحرية عبر هذا الفضاء،
even without this helpful grid,
و حتى دون هذه الشبكة الإيضاحية،
we might be able to paint it ourselves,
قد يمكن أن نرسمها بأنفسنا،
because we would notice that we traveled along straight lines,
لأننا سنلاحظ أننا نتحرك في خط مستقيم،
undeflected straight paths
طرق مستقيمة و غير منحرفة
through the universe.
عبر الكون.
Einstein also realized --
أدرك أينشتاين أيضا --
and this is the real meat of the matter --
و هذه هي صفة المادة الحقيقية --
that if you put energy or mass in the universe,
أنه إذا وضعنا الطاقة أو المادة في الكون،
it would curve space,
فإنها ستجعل الفضاء ينحني.
and a freely falling object
و أن جسما في سقوط حر
would pass by, let's say, the Sun
مارا بقرابة، لنقل، الشمس
and it would be deflected
لسينعطف
along the natural curves in the space.
متبعا إنحرافات الفضاء الطبيعية.
It was Einstein's great general theory of relativity.
و تلك هي نظرية أينشتاين العظيمة للنسبية العامة.
Now even light will be bent by those paths.
ينحرف الضوء أيضا متبعا تلك المسارات.
And you can be bent so much
و يمكن أن يبلغ هذا الإنحراف درجة
that you're caught in orbit around the Sun,
أن تؤسرون في مدار حول الشمس،
as the Earth is, or the Moon around the Earth.
كما هو حال الأرض، أو القمر حول الأرض.
These are the natural curves in space.
هذه هي إنحرافات فضائنا الطبيعية.
What Einstein did not realize
ما لن يدركه أينشتاين
was that, if you took our Sun
هو أنه، إذا أخذنا الشمس
and you crushed it down to six kilometers --
ثم سحقنا بها إلى حجم ست كيلوميترات --
so you took a million times the mass of the Earth
فإذا أخذتم مليون مرة كثلة الأرض
and you crushed it to six kilometers across,
و سحقتم بها إلى حجم ست كيلوميترات،
you would make a black hole,
فستصنعون ثقبا أسود،
an object so dense
جسما جد كثيفا
that if light veered too close, it would never escape --
إلى درجة أنه إذا مر الضوء بقربه، فلن يستطيع الفرار --
a dark shadow against the universe.
خيال مظلم في الكون.
It wasn't Einstein who realized this,
لم يكن أينشتاين من أدرك هذا،
it was Karl Schwarzschild
بل كارل شفارتشيلد
who was a German Jew in World War I --
الذي كان يهوديا ألمانيا خلال الحرب العالمية الأولى --
joined the German army already an accomplished scientist,
إلتحق بالجنود الألمانية و هو عالم متكامل،
working on the Russian front.
كان يعمل على الجبهة الروسية.
I like to imagine Schwarzschild in the war in the trenches
أحب تخيل شفارتشيلد خلال الحرب و هو في الخنادق
calculating ballistic trajectories for cannon fire,
يحسب مسارات قذائف المدفع،
and then, in between,
و بين ذلك،
calculating Einstein's equations --
يحلل معادلات أينشتاين --
as you do in the trenches.
كما يفعل الكل في الخنادق.
And he was reading Einstein's recently published
و لقد كان يقرأ آخر منشورات أينشتاين
general theory of relativity,
النظرية العامة للنسبية،
and he was thrilled by this theory.
و قد كان جد مثار بهذه النظرية.
And he quickly surmised
فخمن و بسرعة
an exact mathematical solution
حلا رياضيا دقيقا
that described something very extraordinary:
يصف شيئا جد إستثنائيا:
curves so strong
إنحناءات جد قوية
that space would rain down into them,
إلى درجة سقوط الفضاء نحوها،
space itself would curve like a waterfall
حيث ينحني الفضاء كشلال مياه
flowing down the throat of a hole.
مندفقا نحو حلقوم ثقب.
And even light could not escape this current.
و لن يستطيع الضوء نفسه الفرار.
Light would be dragged down the hole
سينجرف الضوء نحو الثقب
as everything else would be,
كأي شيء آخر،
and all that would be left would be a shadow.
و كل ما يتبقى هو ظل.
Now he wrote to Einstein,
قام بمراسلة أينشتاين،
and he said, "As you will see,
و قال، "كما سترى،
the war has been kind to me enough.
لقد كرمت علي الحرب بقدر كاف،
Despite the heavy gunfire,
على الرغم من ثقل طلقات النار.
I've been able to get away from it all
تمكنت من الإبتعاد عن كل ذالك
and walk through the land of your ideas."
و من التنزه عبر بلاد أفكارك."
And Einstein was very impressed with his exact solution,
و قد كان أينشتاين جد معجبا بحله الدقيق،
and I should hope also the dedication of the scientist.
كما أتمنى أيضا أن أبلغ مستوى إخلاص العالم.
This is the hardworking scientist under harsh conditions.
هذا هو العالم المتابر رغم الظروف الصعبة.
And he took Schwarzschild's idea
فأخذ فكرة شفارتشيلد
to the Prussian Academy of Sciences the next week.
إلى أكاديمية العلوم البروسية الأسبوع الموالي.
But Einstein always thought black holes were a mathematical oddity.
لكن أينشتاين إعتقد دائما أن الثقب السوداء هي غرائب رياضية.
He did not believe they existed in nature.
لم يصدق بوجودها في الطبيعة.
He thought nature would protect us from their formation.
لقد كان يعتقد أن الطبيعة ستحمينا من تكوينها.
It was decades
عدة عقود
before the term "black hole" was coined
من قبل صيغة إسم "الثقب الأسود"
and people realized
أدرك الناس
that black holes are real astrophysical objects --
أن الثقب السوداء هي أجسام سماوية حقيقية --
in fact they're the death state
إنهم في الحقيقة حالة موت
of very massive stars
نجوم جد ضخمة
that collapse catastrophically
عندما تنهار بصفة كارثية
at the end of their lifetime.
خلال نهاية حياتها.
Now our Sun will not collapse to a black hole.
لن تتمكن الشمس من تكوين ثقب أسود بعد إنهيارها.
It's actually not massive enough.
إنها ليست ضخمة بما فيه الكفاية.
But if we did a little thought experiment --
لكن إذا أنجزنا تجربة خيالية صغيرة --
as Einstein was very fond of doing --
كما كان أينشتاين يحب أن يفعل --
we could imagine
يمكن أن نتخيل
putting the Sun crushed down to six kilometers,
سحق الشمس إلى حجم ست كيلوميترات،
and putting a tiny little Earth around it in orbit,
و لنضع كوكب أرض صغير جدا في مدار حوله،
maybe 30 kilometers
ربما ٣٠ كيلوميتر
outside of the black-hole sun.
بعيدا عن مركز الثقب الأسود.
And it would be self-illuminated,
و لنعتبر أنه يضيء نفسه بنفسه،
because now the Sun's gone, we have no other source of light --
لأن الشمس قد ذهبت الآن، ليس لنا أي مصدر ضوء آخر --
so let's make our little Earth self-illuminated.
فلنجعل إذا أرضنا الصغيرة مضائة بنفسها.
And you would realize you could put the Earth in a happy orbit
فستدركون أنه من الممكن وضع الأرض فوق مدار آمن
even 30 km
على مسافة ٣٠ كيلوميتر
outside of this crushed black hole.
خارج هذا الثقب الأسود المسحوق.
This crushed black hole
يمكن لهذا الثقب الأسود
actually would fit inside Manhattan, more or less.
أن يوضع داخل مانهاتن، تقريبا.
It might spill off into the Hudson a little bit
من الممكن أن يغطي جزءا من الهودسون
before it destroyed the Earth.
قبل تحطيم الأرض.
But basically that's what we're talking about.
لكن أساسا هذا هو الحجم الذي نتكلم عنه.
We're talking about an object that you could crush down
إنا نتكلم عن جسم نستطيع سحقه
to half the square area of Manhattan.
إلى نصف مساحة مانهاتن.
So we move this Earth very close --
و بذلك نحرك هذه الأرض على مسافة جد قريبة --
30 kilometers outside --
على بعد ٣٠ كيلوميتر --
and we notice it's perfectly fine orbiting around the black hole.
و نلاحظ أنها على أحسن حال في مدارها حول الثقب الأسود.
There's a sort of myth
هنالك خرافة تنص على أن
that black holes devour everything in the universe,
الثقب السوداء تلتهم كل شيء في الكون،
but you actually have to get very close to fall in.
لكن في حقيقة الأمر يجب الإقتراب كثيرا للسقوط فيها.
But what's very impressive is that, from our vantage point,
لكن الأكثر مذهلا في الأمر هو أنه، من موقع مشاهدتنا،
we can always see the Earth.
يمكننا دائما رؤية الأرض.
It cannot hide behind the black hole.
لا يمكن لها التخفي وراء الثقب الأسود.
The light from the Earth, some of it falls in,
إن الضوء القادم من الأرض، يسقط بعضه في الثقب الأسود،
but some of it gets lensed around and brought back to us.
لكن يرجع إلينا البعض بعد إلتفافه حول الثقب الأسود.
So you can't hide anything behind a black hole.
و بذالك لا يمكن إخفاء أي شيء وراء ثقب أسود.
If this were Battlestar Galactica
إذا كانت ذالك سلسلة "باطلسطار كالاكتيكا"
and you're fighting the Cylons,
و إذا كنتم تقاتلون "السايلونز"،
don't hide behind the black hole.
فلا تخفوا أنفسكم وراء الثقب الأسود.
They can see you.
فإنهم يستطيعون رؤيتكم.
Now, our Sun will not collapse to a black hole --
لن تتمكن الشمس من الإنهيار إلى ثقب أسود؛
it's not massive enough --
فهي ليسي ضخمة بما فيه الكفاية،
but there are tens of thousands of black holes in our galaxy.
لكن هنالك مئات من آلاف الثقب السوداء في مجرتنا.
And if one were to eclipse the Milky Way,
و إذا قام واحد منها بحجب درب التبانة،
this is what it would look like.
فسيبدوا ذالك على هذه الهيئة.
We would see a shadow of that black hole
سنرى خيالا لهذا الثقب الأسود
against the hundred billion stars
فوق مئات المليارات من النجوم
in the Milky Way Galaxy and its luminous dust lanes.
الموجودة بدرب التبانة و على زقاق غبارها المضيء.
And if we were to fall towards this black hole,
و إذا سقطنا نحو هذا الثقب الأسود،
we would see all of that light lensed around it,
فسنرى كل ذالك الضوء الذي يلتف حوله،
and we could even start to cross into that shadow
و سنعبر الحد نحو داخل الظلام
and really not notice that anything dramatic had happened.
دون أن نلاحظ أي تغير مفجع.
It would be bad if we tried to fire our rockets and get out of there
و سيكون دون أي فائدة إذا قمنا بتشغيل محركاتنا للخروج من هنالك
because we couldn't,
لأننا لن نستطيع أبدا،
anymore than light can escape.
أي شيء حتى الضوء لا يستطيع الفرار.
But even though the black hole is dark from the outside,
و رغم أن الثقب الأسود يبدو مظلما من الخارج،
it's not dark on the inside,
فإنه ليس مظلما في داخله،
because all of the light from the galaxy can fall in behind us.
لأن كل الضوء القادم من المجرة يسقط فيه
And even though, due to a relativistic effect known as time dilation,
و رغم أنه، نتيجة لمفعول نسبي يعرف بتمدد الوقت،
our clocks would seem to slow down
سيبدو و كأن ساعاتنا تبطئ
relative to galactic time,
بالنسبة للوقت المجري،
it would look as though the evolution of the galaxy
سيبدو و كأن تطور المجرة
had been sped up and shot at us,
قد تسرع ثم قذف إلينا،
right before we were crushed to death by the black hole.
قبيل سحقنا المميت من قبل الثقب الأسود.
It would be like a near-death experience
سيكون ذالك تجربة مشابهة للحظة الإقتراب من الموت
where you see the light at the end of the tunnel,
حيث ترون النور عند نهاية النفق،
but it's a total death experience.
إلا أنها تجربة موت كاملة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And there's no way of telling anybody
و ليس هنالك أي طريقة لإخبار أي أحد
about the light at the end of the tunnel.
عن النور عند نهاية النفق.
Now we've never seen a shadow like this of a black hole,
لم نستطع قط مشاهدة ظل ثقب أسود كهذا،
but black holes can be heard,
لكن يمكن سماع الثقب السوداء،
even if they're not seen.
رغم أنه لم يتم مشاهدتهم.
Imagine now taking an astrophysically realistic situation --
لنتخيل الآن موقفا حقيقيا في الكون --
imagine two black holes that have lived a long life together.
لنتخيل ثقبين أسودين قضيا حياة طويلة معا.
Maybe they started as stars
ربما قد إبتدءا كنجمين
and collapsed to two black holes --
ثم إنهارا إلى ثقبين أسودين --
each one 10 times the mass of the Sun.
كل واحد منهما يمثل ١٠ أضعاف كثلة الشمس.
So now we're going to crush them down to 60 kilometers across.
و لنقم الآن بكسفهما إلى مسافة ٦٠ كيلومتر.
They can be spinning
يمكن أن يلتفا
hundreds of times a second.
مئات المرات في الثانية.
At the end of their lives,
عند نهاية حياتهم،
they're going around each other very near the speed of light.
يدور كل واحد منهما حول الآخر قريبا من سرعة الضوء.
So they're crossing thousands of kilometers
ههما يعبران آلاف الكيلوميترات
in a fraction of a second,
خلال جزء من الثانية.
and as they do so, they not only curve space,
و خلال ذالك، فإنهما لا يغيران منحنى الفضاء فقط،
but they leave behind in their wake
بل يتركان على عقبيهما
a ringing of space,
فضاء رنانا،
an actual wave on space-time.
موجة حقيقية في الزمكان.
Space squeezes and stretches
فيتقلص الفضاء ثم يتمدد
as it emanates out from these black holes
خلال إنبعاث الموجة من هذين الثقبين الأسودين
banging on the universe.
و هما يطرقان على الكون.
And they travel out into the cosmos
و ترحل هذه الموجات عبر الكون
at the speed of light.
بسرعة الضوء.
This computer simulation
يأتينا هذا النموذج
is due to a relativity group at NASA Goddard.
من قبل مجموعة النسبية في نازا كودارد.
It took almost 30 years for anyone in the world to crack this problem.
لقد تطلب الأمر ٣٠ سنة لكي يتمكن أي أحد من حل هذه المسألة.
This was one of the groups.
هذه واحدة من بين المجموعات الذين وجدوا الحل.
It shows two black holes in orbit around each other,
و يمثل النموذج ثقبين أسودين كل واحد في مدار حول الآخر،
again, with these helpfully painted curves.
مرافقا بهذه المنحنيات المساعدة على الفهم.
And if you can see -- it's kind of faint --
و إذا تمكنتم من الرؤية -- إن الصورة خافتة قليلا --
but if you can see the red waves emanating out,
و لكن إذا تمكنتم من رؤية التموجات الحمراء المنبعثة،
those are the gravitational waves.
هذه هي الأمواج الثقالية.
They're literally the sounds of space ringing,
إنها أصوات رنين الفضاء،
and they will travel out from these black holes at the speed of light
و سترحل عن الثقب السوداء بسرعة الضوء
as they ring down and coalesce
و هي تتقارب لتتحد
to one spinning, quiet black hole
في ثقب أسود هادىء
at the end of the day.
عند نهاية اليوم.
If you were standing near enough,
إذا وقفتم بالقرب من ذلك،
your ear would resonate
فترتد آذانكم
with the squeezing and stretching of space.
نتيجة لتقلص و تمدد الفضاء.
You would literally hear the sound.
ستسمعون الصوت.
Now of course, your head would be squeezed and stretched unhelpfully,
و بطبيعة الأمر، سيتقلص و يتمدد رأسكم أيضا،
so you might have trouble understanding what's going on.
و لربما لن تستطيعوا فهم ما يحدث.
But I'd like to play for you
أود أن أسمعكم
the sound that we predict.
الصوت الذي نتوقع صدوره.
This is from my group --
يأتي هذا من المجموعة التي أنتمي إليها --
a slightly less glamorous computer modeling.
نموذج كمبيوتر أقل جاذبية.
Imagine a lighter black hole
تخيلوا ثقبا أسودا أقل ثقلا
falling into a very heavy black hole.
و هو يسقط نحو ثقب أسود آخر ثقيل جدا.
The sound you're hearing
تستمعون هنا إلى صوت
is the light black hole banging on space
الثقب الأسود الخفيف و هو يطرق الفضاء
each time it gets close.
كلما إقترب من الآخر.
If it gets far away, it's a little too quiet.
و يهدأ الصوت قليلا عندما يقوم بالإبتعاد.
But it comes in like a mallet,
لكنه يبدوا كضرب مطرقة،
and it literally cracks space,
و هو يكسر بذالك الفضاء حوله،
wobbling it like a drum.
فيجعله يرتد كالطبل.
And we can predict what the sound will be.
و يمكن لنا توقع الهيئة التي سيصدر عليها الصوت.
We know that, as it falls in,
إنا نعلم، أنه كلما سقط،
it gets faster and it gets louder.
كلما إرتفعت سرعته و زاد ضجيجه.
And eventually,
و في النهاية،
we're going to hear the little guy just fall into the bigger guy.
سنسمع الأصغر منهما يسقط على الآخر.
(Thumping)
(إرتطام)
Then it's gone.
و يختفي بعد ذلك.
Now I've never heard it that loud -- it's actually more dramatic.
لم أستمع له بهذا العلو من قبل -- إنه في حقيقة الأمر أكثر ثأثيرا.
At home it sounds kind of anticlimactic.
ينقص تأثيره عندما ننصت له في المنزل.
It's sort of like ding, ding, ding.
و يبدوا هكذا، ديك، ديك، ديك.
This is another sound from my group.
و هذا صوت آخر من المجموعة التي أعمل بها.
No, I'm not showing you any images,
لا، لن أريكم أي صورة،
because black holes don't leave behind
لأن الثقب السوداء لا تترك ورائها
helpful trails of ink,
آثار حبر مساعدة،
and space is not painted,
و لا ترسم أي شيء على الفضاء،
showing you the curves.
لإيضاح المنحنيات التي قد تشكلت.
But if you were to float by in space on a space holiday
لكن إذا مررتم بقرب ذالك في رحلة فضائية سياحية
and you heard this,
و سمعتم هذا الصوت،
you want to get moving.
فإنه من الأفضل ألا تتوقفوا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Want to get away from the sound.
من الأفضل أن تبتعدوا عن مصدر الصوت.
Both black holes are moving.
يتحرك كلا الثقبين الأسودين.
Both black holes are getting closer together.
و يقترب بعضهما من بعض.
In this case, they're both wobbling quite a lot.
و يرتد كلاهما كثيرا في هذه الحالة.
And then they're going to merge.
و سيقومان بالإندماج في النهاية.
(Thumping)
(إرتطام)
Now it's gone.
لقد إختفى.
Now that chirp is very characteristic of black holes merging --
يميز هذا الصوت إندماج ثقبين أسودين --
that it chirps up at the end.
و تظهر هذه الزقزقة عند نهاية الإندماج.
Now that's our prediction
فهذا الآن هو توقعنا
for what we'll see.
لما سنراه يوما ما.
Luckily we're at this safe distance in Long Beach, California.
سنكون و بقليل من الحظ على مسافة آمنة في "لونك بيتش، كاليفورنيا".
And surely, somewhere in the universe
و من المؤكد، أنه في مكان ما من الكون
two black holes have merged.
قد قام ثقبين أسودين بالإندماج.
And surely, the space around us
و من المؤكد، أن الفضاء حولنا
is ringing
يرن
after traveling maybe a million light years, or a million years,
بعد رحلة قد إمتدت على ملايين السنوات الضوئية، أو ملايين السنوات،
at the speed of light to get to us.
لتأتي إلينا في سرعة الضوء.
But the sound is too quiet for any of us to ever hear.
لكن الصوت جد خافت ليتمكن أي أحد منا أن يسمعه.
There are very industrious experiments being built on Earth --
هنالك تجارب جدية يتم إنشاءها على الأرض --
one called LIGO --
تسمى واحدة منها "ليكو" --
which will detect deviations
و التي ستكشف عن تغيرات
in the squeezing and stretching of space
في تقلص و إمتداد الفضاء
at less than the fraction of a nucleus of an atom
بمقدار أقل من جزء من نوية الذرة
over four kilometers.
في مسافة أربع كيلرميترات.
It's a remarkably ambitious experiment,
و إنها لتجربة جد طموحة
and it's going to be at advanced sensitivity
و ستزداد حساسيتها
within the next few years -- to pick this up.
مع السنوات القادمة -- للتمكن من إستكشاف هذا.
There's also a mission proposed for space,
هنالك أيضا مشروع آخر في الفضاء الخارجي،
which hopefully will launch in the next ten years,
و التي نتمنى أن يتم بناءها خلال العشر سنوات القادمة،
called LISA.
يطلق عليها إسم "ليسا".
And LISA will be able to see super-massive black holes --
و ستكون ليسا قادرة على رؤية الثقوب السوداء كبيرة الحجم --
black holes millions or billions of times
ثقوب سوداء تزن ملايين أوبلاين المرات
the mass of the Sun.
كثلة الشمس.
In this Hubble image, we see two galaxies.
نرى مجرتين على هذه الصورة الملتقطة بمنظار "هبل".
They look like they're frozen in some embrace.
تبدوان و كأنها مجمدة في تناسق.
And each one probably harbors
و من المحتمل أن كل واحدة
a super-massive black hole at its core.
تستضيف في جوفها ثقبا أسودا عظيما.
But they're not frozen;
لكنهما ليستا جامدتين،
they're actually merging.
إنهما في حقيقة الأمر في طريق الإندماج.
These two black holes are colliding,
يتجه هذين الثقبين الأسودين نحو الإصطدام،
and they will merge over a billion-year time scale.
و سيندمجان خلال مدة مليار سنة تقريبا.
It's beyond our human perception
يتعدى قدرتنا البشرية
to pick up a song of that duration.
تسجيل أغنية بهذه المدة.
But LISA could see the final stages
لكن يمكن "ليسا" رؤية المراحل الأخيرة
of two super-massive black holes
لثقبين أسودين عظيمين
earlier in the universe's history,
خلال مرحلة ماضية من تاريخ الكون،
the last 15 minutes before they fall together.
الدقائق ١٥ الأخيرة قبيل إنحطامهما.
And it's not just black holes,
و لا يطبق ذالك سوى على الثقب السوداء،
but it's also any big disturbance in the universe --
بل أيضا على أي إضطراب كبير في الكون --
and the biggest of them all is the Big Bang.
و أعظمها جميعا هو "الإنفجار العظيم"
When that expression was coined, it was derisive --
عندما أصيغت هذه العبارة، كان ذالك بصفة هزلية --
like, "Oh, who would believe in a Big Bang?"
مثل، "آه، من سيصدق وجود إنفجار عظيم؟"
But now it actually might be more technically accurate
لكنها الآن يمكن أن تكون أكثر دقة،
because it might bang.
لأن الإنفجار ممكن؛
It might make a sound.
و يمكنه إصدار صوت.
This animation from my friends at Proton Studios
يمثل هذا النموذج الذي حصلت عليه من قبل أصدقائي في "بروتون ستوديوس"
shows looking at the Big Bang from the outside.
رؤية خارجية للإنفجار العظيم.
We don't ever want to do that actually. We want to be inside the universe
في حقيقة الأمر لا نريد أن نفعل هذا؛ نريد أن نرى داخل الكون،
because there's no such thing as standing outside the universe.
لأن الوقوف خارج الكون ليس شيئا حقيقيا.
So imagine you're inside the Big Bang.
تخيلوا إذن أنكم داخل الإنفجار العظيم.
It's everywhere, it's all around you,
أنه في كل مكان، يحيطكم من جميع الإتجاهات،
and the space is wobbling chaotically.
و أن الفضاء يرتد في عشوائية.
Fourteen billion years pass
١٤ مليار سنة من قبل
and this song is still ringing all around us.
و ما تزال هذه الأغنية ترن حولنا.
Galaxies form,
تتشكل المجرات،
and generations of stars form in those galaxies,
و أجيال كاملة من النجوم داخل هاته المجرات.
and around one star,
و حول نجم واحد،
at least one star,
على الأقل،
is a habitable planet.
هنالك كوكب مسكون.
And here we are frantically building these experiments,
و ههنا نحن نصنع في حمة كل هذه التجارب،
doing these calculations, writing these computer codes.
نقوم بكل هذه الحسابات، و نكتب كل هذه البرامج على الكمبيوتر.
Imagine a billion years ago,
تخيلوا مليار سنة من قبل،
two black holes collided.
إصطدام ثقبين أسودين.
That song has been ringing through space
و منذ ذلك و هذه الأغنية ترن عبر الفضاء
for all that time.
طيلة كل هذه المدة.
We weren't even here.
لم نكن هنا خلال ذالك.
It gets closer and closer --
و تقترب منا أكثر فأكثر --
40,000 years ago, we're still doing cave paintings.
٤٠٠٠٠ سنة من قبل، كنا مازلنا نرسم على جدران الكهوف.
It's like hurry, build your instruments.
يجب أن نسرع، لنصنع آلاتنا.
It's getting closer and closer, and in 20 ...
إنه يقترب، و بعد ٢٠ ...
whatever year it will be
أو أي سنة سيتحقق ذالك
when our detectors are finally at advanced sensitivity --
عندما تصل كاشفاتنا إلى الحساسية المناسبة --
we'll build them, we'll turn on the machines
سنصنعهم، ثم سنقوم بتشغيلهم
and, bang, we'll catch it -- the first song from space.
و أنذاك سنلتقطها -- أول أغنية من الفضاء.
If it was the Big Bang we were going to pick up,
إذا كنا لنسجل صوت الإنفجار العظيم،
it would sound like this.
فسيكون شيئا مثل هذا.
(Static) It's a terrible sound.
(ضجيج) إنه صوت جد مزعج.
It's literally the definition of noise.
و إنه التعريف الدقيق للضجيج.
It's white noise; it's such a chaotic ringing.
إنه الضجيج الأبيض، رنين جد عشوائي.
But it's around us everywhere, presumably,
نفترض أنه يوجد حولنا،
if it hasn't been wiped out
إذا لم يتم محيه
by some other process in the universe.
من طرف ظاهرة أخرى في الكون.
And if we pick it up, it will be music to our ears
و إذا تمكنا من تسجيله، فسيكون موسيقى لآذاننا،
because it will be the quiet echo
لأنه سيكون الصدى الهادئ
of that moment of our creation,
للحظة الخلق،
of our observable universe.
خلق كوننا المنظور.
So within the next few years,
و بذالك خلال الأعوام القادمة،
we'll be able to turn up the soundtrack a little bit,
سنتمكن من كشف على القليل من هذا الشريط الصوتي،
render the universe in audio.
و تحليل الكون عن طريق الصوت.
But if we detect those earliest moments,
و إذا كشفنا عن هذه اللحظات الأولية،
it'll bring us that much closer
ستقربنا هذه المعلومات
to an understanding of the Big Bang,
من فهم الإنفجار العظيم،
which brings us that much closer
مما يقربنا أكثر
to asking some of the hardest, most elusive, questions.
من طرح أصعب، و أغمض، الأسئلة.
If we run the movie of our universe backwards,
إذا قمنا بمشاهدة شريط الكون راجعين إلى أول الزمان،
we know that there was a Big Bang in our past,
نعلم أن هنالك إنفجار عظيم في ماضي زمننا،
and we might even hear the cacophonous sound of it,
حتى أنه يمكننا سماع ضجيجه،
but was our Big Bang the only Big Bang?
لكن، هل كان إنفجارنا العظيم الإنفجار الوحيد؟
I mean we have to ask, has it happened before?
أعني، يجب علينا طرح السؤال، هل حدث ذالك من قبل؟
Will it happen again?
و هل سيحدث من جديد؟
I mean, in the spirit of rising to TED's challenge
في طموح للعلو إلى تحدي TED
to reignite wonder,
و إيقاد شعلة التعجب،
we can ask questions, at least for this last minute,
يمكننا طرح أسئلة، على الأقل خلال هذه الداقائق الأخيرة،
that honestly might evade us forever.
و التي يمكن أن تشغل بالنا إلى الأبد.
But we have to ask:
لكن يجب علينا أن نتساءل:
Is it possible that our universe
هل من الممكن أن كوننا
is just a plume off of some greater history?
هو قطعة من تاريخ أعظم؟
Or, is it possible that we're just a branch off of a multiverse --
أو، هل من الممكن أننا سوى فرع من كون متعدد --
each branch with its own Big Bang in its past --
يتوفر كل فرع منه على إنفجاره العظيم --
maybe some of them with black holes playing drums,
و ربما يوجد في بعض منهم ثقب سوداء تدق الطبل،
maybe some without --
و ربما البعض دون ذلك --
maybe some with sentient life, and maybe some without --
ربما بعض منهم يحوي الحياة، و ربما البعض بدون --
not in our past, not in our future,
لا يوجدون في ماضينا، و لا يوجدون في مستقبلنا،
but somehow fundamentally connected to us?
لكن و بطريقة ما، جد مرتبطين بنا؟
So we have to wonder, if there is a multiverse,
و بذلك يجب أن نتساءل، هل هنالك كون متعدد،
in some other patch of that multiverse,
و في أحد البقع من هذا الكون المتعدد،
are there creatures?
هل هنالك مخلوقات؟
Here's my multiverse creatures.
ها هي هنا مخلوقات كوني المتعدد.
Are there other creatures in the multiverse,
هل هنالك مخلوقات أخرى في الكون المتعدد،
wondering about us
يتساءلون بدورهم عن وجودنا
and wondering about their own origins?
و عن أصول خلقهم؟
And if they are,
و إذا كانوا موجودين حقا،
I can imagine them as we are,
فإني أتخيلهم على نفس حالتنا،
calculating, writing computer code,
يقومون بحسابات، يكتبون برامجا على الكمبيوتر،
building instruments,
يصنعون أجهزة،
trying to detect that faintest sound
ليكشفوا عن ذالك الصوت الخافت
of their origins
المعبر عن أصولهم
and wondering who else is out there.
و يتساءلون أيضا هل هنالك أحد غيرهم في الفضاء الخارجي.
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرا لكم. شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)